We're going to talk about shortest paths,
我们今天讲最短路径算法
and we're going to talk about shortest paths for three lectures.
我们大概要讲它三次课
So, this is a trilogy.
最短路径三部曲
Today will be Shortest Paths One.
今天讲最短路径第一部
I've been watching far too many versions of Star Wars this weekend.
这个星期我看了太多个版本的星球大战了
I saw the musical yesterday, matinee.
我昨天看的是音乐剧 白天场的
That was an MIT musical.
那是MIT自己的音乐剧
That was fun, of all three plays
很有意思 一共三场
of all three movies in about four hours, that was a bit long
三场加起来四个小时 时间略长
and then I saw the one-man show on Friday.
然后我星期五看的是个人秀
One-man Star Wars: the original three movies in one hour.
一个人的星战 一个小时内演了三场
That was the opposite of too long.
那熊孩子真会玩儿
Both were fun.
两场都很过瘾
So I get my trilogy fix.
现在开始我的三部曲
All episodes, first we're going to start with The New Hope,
我们先从《新希望》开始
and we're going to talk about the shortest paths problem
我们会介绍 什么是最短路径问题
and solve one particular problem of it,
然后讲解其中的一部分问题
a very interesting version.
一些非常有趣的问题
And then we're going to look at increasingly
然后我们会慢慢地接触到
more general versions as we go on.
更多的、更一般化的问题
Shortest paths are sort of an application of dynamic programming,
最短路径算法是一种动态规划的应用
which we saw last week, and greedy...
就是我们上周讲的 还有贪...
and greedy algorithms, which we also saw last week.
还有贪心算法 我们上周也讲过的
So, we're going to build that and get some pretty interesting
我们一会要实现它 用一些很有趣的算法
algorithms for an important problem, which is
来解决一些重要的问题 例如
how to get from Alderon to,
如果从奥德隆出发...
I don't know, Cambridge as quickly as possible,
呃...怎么走才能最快到剑桥？
OK, when you live in a graph.
好吧 假设是在地图上走的话
So, there's geometric shortest paths which is a little bit harder.
几何学上有几种最短路径 那比较复杂
Here, we're just going to look at shortest paths in graphs.
但这里 我们只关注图的最短路径
Now, hopefully you all know what a path in a graph is.
我想你们都应该知道 图的路径是什么了
But, so, very quick review in particular
但还是简单地回顾下
because we're going to be looking at weighted graphs.
因为我们准备研究加权的图
So, the usual setup: suppose we have directed graph, G,
那一般前提是 假设我们有个有向图G
have some vertices, some edges.
有一些顶点 一些边
We have edge weights, make it a little more interesting.
已知边的权重 这会使得图更加有趣
So, this is just a real number on each edge.
权重就是每条边上的一个实数
So, edge weights are usually given by function, w.
权重可以用函数W来表示
For every edge, you get a real number.
对于每条边 都有一个实数
And then, if we look at the paths in the graph,
然后 当我们观察图的路径时
so we're going to use some simple notation for paths
我们会用一些简单的符号来表示路径
called a path, p, starts at some vertex,
比如路径p 起点是某个顶点
and it goes to some other vertex, and so on.
经过另一个顶点 等等
Say the last vertex is v_k, and
最后一个顶点是v_k
each of these should be a directed edge in the digraph,
这些都是有向图里面的有向边
So, this is a directed path.
所以 这是一条有向的路径
path to respect edges in here.
它由对应的这些边组成
And, we'll say that the weight of such a path
然后 一条路径的总权值
is just the sum of the weights of the edges along the path.
等于路径上的各边的权值的总和
And, we'll call that w(p).
我们令此为w(p)
This is sum, i equals one to k minus one of w(v_i, v_(i+1)) plus one.
它等于∑w(v_i, v_(i+1)) i从1到k-1
OK, so just to rub it in,
好的 把它画出来
and in particular, how general this can be,
那在这里 它一般会是这个样子
we have some path, it starts at some vertex,
我们有一条路径 它从某个顶点开始
there's some edge weights along the way.
它经过的每条边上有一些权值
This is some arbitrary path in the graph,
这代表图里任意一条路径
in some hypothetical graph.
在某一幅假想图里的路径
OK, this is mainly to point out that
好 这里主要想讲的是
some of the edge weights could be negative.
有些边的权值可能是负值
Some of them could be zero.
也有一些可能等于0
This sum here is minus two.
这里的和等于-2
So, the weight of this path is minus two.
所以这路径的权值为-2
And, presumably, the graph is much bigger than this.
这幅图可能比这儿要大得多
This is just one path in the graph.
这只是图里面的一条路径
We're usually thinking about simple paths that can't repeat a vertex.
我们通常考虑的简单路径不会重复经过一个顶点
But, sometimes we allow that.
但有时候 我们又允许有这种情况
And then, what we care about is the shortest path,
然后 我们关心的是最短的路径
or a shortest path. Again, this may not be unique,
或者是某一条最短路径 因为可能不止一条
but we'll still usually call it the shortest path.
但我们通常会称之为最短路径
So, we want the shortest path from some A to some B.
我们想求从A点到B点的最短路径
Or, we'll call the vertices u and v.
我们设这两点为u和v
And we want this to be some path of minimum possible weight,
我们想让路径的总权值尽可能地小
subject to starting at u, and going to v.
使得从u到v的路径最短
OK, so that's what we're looking for.
好的 这就是我们想要的
In general, give you a vertex, u, give you a vertex, v,
一般来说 给你起点u和终点v
find a shortest path as quickly as possible.
如果要最快地找出最短路径
What's a good algorithm for that?
有什么好的算法？
That's the topic for the next three lectures.
这就是接下来三次课要讲的内容
We'll usually think about a slightly simpler problem,
我们通常会思考一个简单一点的问题
which is just computing the weight of that path,
就是如何计算路径的权值
which is essentially computing the distance from A to B.
说白了就是计算从A到B的距离
So, we'll call this the shortest path weight from u to v.
我们把从u到v的最短路径的权值
And, we'll denote it by delta of (u,v), delta .
用δ(u,v)来表示 这个小写的δ
So, I mean, it's the weight of the shortest path,
那么 它等于最短路径的权值
or a weight of every shortest path.
或者说 每条最短路径的权值
Or, in other words,
也就是说
it's the Min over the weight of each path from u to v.
它等于所有从u到v的路径中的最小值
So, p here is a path.
这里的p是一条路径
OK, so you just consider,
你只要这么想
there could be a lot of different paths.
这里可能有许多不同的路径
There could, in principle, be infinitely many,
理论上 这有无数条路径
if you're allowed to repeat vertices.
如果允许重复经过顶点的话
You look at all those paths hypothetically.
假设 你把所有这些路径都算一遍
You take the minimum weight.
然后取最小的权值
Question?
有问题？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Good. My next question was going to be,
[教授]:问得好 我的下一个问题是
when do shortest paths not exist?
什么时候 这条最短路径会不存在?
And you've hit upon one version,
你们已经遇到一次这种情况了
which is when you have negative edge weights.
就是出现负权值的边的时候
So, in principle, when you have negative edge weights,
原则上 当你有负值的边时
some shortest paths may not exist
最短路径就可能不存在
in the sense that there is no shortest paths.
也就是不存在最短路径
There are no shortest paths.
我们找不到最短路径
There is no shortest path from u to v.
u和v之间没有最短路径
OK, in particular, if I have two vertices, u and v,
但实际上 如果我有两个顶点u和v
and I want the shortest path between them,
我想得到它们之间的最短路径
and I have negative edge weights,
而其中又有带负值的边
well, this is fine. I mean,
这其实也是可行的
I can still compute the weight
因为我还是能够计算...
of a path that has negative weights.
一条带负值的路径的权值
But when specifically won't I have a
但什么情况下 才会真正地...
single shortest path from u to v?
没有一条从u到v的最短路径？
So, go ahead.
所以 想想看
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Good.
[教授]:好
So, if I can find the cycle somewhere along here
如果我在某处找到了一个环
whose total weight, say,
它总的权值是...
the sum of all the weights of these images is negative,
这些权值的总和是负的
then I get there, I go around as many times as I want.
如果我在这里 不断地跑这个环
I keep decreasing the weight
这样总权值就会不断减少
because the weight is negative.
因为这条环是负的
I decrease it by some fixed amount,
我每走一次就减一个定值
and then I can go to v.
然后我再走到v
So, as long as there is a negative weights cycle reachable
只要是在从u到v的路径中
from u that can also reach v,
经过了一个负环
then there's no shortest path
这样便不存在最短路径
because if I take any particular path,
因为无论我选择哪条路径
I can make it shorter by going around a couple more times.
我都可以不断走负环来变得更短
So, in some sense, this is not really a minimum.
所以在某种程度上 这不是真的最小值
It's more like an infimum for those who
对于某些数学痴来说
who like to get fancy about such things.
这更应该说是一个下确界
But we'll just say that delta of (u,v)
但在这里 我们会记δ(u,v)
is minus infinity in this case.
为负无穷
There's a negative weights cycle from u to v.
因为u和v之间有一个负环
So, that's one case we have to worry about in some sense.
所以 这种情况是我们需要注意的
But, as long as there are no negative weight cycles,
然而 只要没有负环的话
delta of (u,v) will be something bigger than minus infinity,
δ(u,v)就会是大于负无穷的值
some finite...bounded below by some finite value
有一个有限的...有一个有限的下界
even if you could have negative weights,
就算你有负权的边
but still no negative weights cycle
但没有形成负环的话
for example, there might not be any cycles in your graph.
比如说 你的图里没有任何的环
So that's still interesting.
那这问题就还值得探讨
And, I guess it's useful to note that
而且 我觉得这样想会更好懂
you can get from A to B in negative infinite time.
如果你从A到B花的时间是负无穷
It's great, it's time travel,
恭喜你 你穿越了
if the weights happen that correspond to time.
假如权值表示的是时间的话
But when else might shortest paths not exist?
还有什么情况下最短路径不存在？
So, this is one case,
刚才讲的是一种情况
but there's another, simpler case.
但还有另一种简单的情况
It's not connected. There might not be any path from u to v.
顶点没有连起来 从u到v可能一条路径都没有
This set might be empty.
路径集合为空
There may be no path from u to v.
可能一条从u到v的路径都没有
Here we have to define what happens,
这里我们要下一个定义
and here, we'll say it's infinity
当u到v之间没有路径时
if there's no path from u to v.
我们设它为无穷大
So, there are these exceptional cases
以上就是特殊情况
plus infinity and minus infinity, which are pretty intuitive
一个正无穷 一个负无穷 显而易见
because it takes a really long time
因为它真的要花超长的时间
to get from u to v if there's no path there.
来从u到达v
You can't get there from here.
你没法从这儿去到那儿
OK, but that's the definition.
好的 定义完了
Most of the time, this is the case we care about, of course.
当然 在很多时候 我们都要留意这些情况
Usually this is a finite set.
但通常它是一个有限集
OK, good, so that's the definition.
好的 这是我们给的定义
Now let me tell you,
现在我说
We're going to get a few basic structural properties
接下来 我们要学习一些
about shortest paths that will allow us to
最短路径的基本特征
obtain good algorithms finding these paths when they exist.
以此来构造好的算法 找出存在的最短路径
And, in particular,
特别是
we want to use ideas from dynamic programming.
我们想用上动态规划的思想
So, if I want to use dynamic programming
所以 如果我想用到动态规划
to solve shortest paths,
来解决最短路径问题
what do I need to establish?
我要确定些什么？
What's the first thing I should check?
我首先要注意的是什么？
You've all implemented dynamic programming by now,
你们都试过写动态规划
so should make complete sense hopefully,
应该都有一个全面的理解
at least more sense than it did a couple of weeks ago,
至少比前几周没接触过的时候要好
last week, when we learned it.
上一周 我们都学过了
Dynamic programming is something that grows on you.
动态规划的学习是要积累的
Every year I think I understand it better than the previous year.
每一年我都觉得 自己对它有了更好的理解
But, in particular,
但有一点
when you learned dynamic programming in this class,
当你在课堂上学习了动态规划
there is this nice key property that you should check.
你们要注意到一个关键的性质
Yeah? Optimal substructure: good.
什么？ 最优子结构  有见地
This is the phrase you should keep in mind.
这个短语你们要牢记
It's not really enough for dynamic programming to be
虽然这个还不足以令动态规划
useful in an efficient way,
得到有效利用
but it at least tells you that you should..
但至少告诉你你该干什么
you should be able to try to apply it.
你们应该能试着用上它
That's a pretty weak statement, but
这虽然是个很弱的命题 但是
it's something that you should check.
也是你们要注意的一点
It's definitely pretty much a necessary condition for
这对于动态规划的有效性而言
dynamic programming to make sense.
绝对是一个必要条件
And so, optimal some structure here means that
那么 最优结构表示的是
if I take some shortest path,
当我选定一条最短路径时
and I look at a subpath of that shortest path,
我再观察这条最短路径的子路径
I claimed that it too is a shortest path,
我肯定它也是一条最短路径
OK, with its respective endpoints;
子路径对应的两个端点
obviously not between the same endpoints.
显然不都是原路径的两端点
But if I have some shortest path between two endpoints,
但如果两端点间 有一条最短路径的话
I take any subpath and that's also the shortest path.
我取的任意一条子路径 都是最短子路径
This is one version of optimal substructure.
这个最优子结构的一个版本
This one turns out to be true for this setup.
这对于这里的前提条件是成立的
And, how should I prove an optimal substructure property?
那么 我们该怎么证明一个最优子结构的性质？
Cut and paste.
剪贴法
Yep, that works here too.
在这里也用得上
I mean, this isn't always true.
我的意思是 它不是总是有用
But it's a good technique here.
但这里它是一个好方法
So, we're going to think about,
好 让我们想想看
and I'll do essentially a proof by picture here.
然后我准备画幅图来证明
So, suppose you have some subpath of some shortest path.
好的 假如你有一些最短路径的子路径
So, let's say the subpath is x to y.
我们设子路径从x到y
And, the path goes from u to v.
最优路径是从u到v的
So, we assume that (u,v) is a shortest path.
所以我们假设(u,v)是最短路径
We want to prove that (x,y) is a shortest path.
我们要证明(x,y)也是最短路径
Well, suppose (x,y) isn't a shortest path.
好的 假设(x,y)不是最短路径
Then there is some shorter path that goes from x to y.
那么x到y之间就有一条更短的路径
But, if you have some shorter path from x to y than this one.
但如果你在x到y之间有一条更短的路径
Then I should just erase this part
那么我只要把这一部分子路径
of the shortest path from u to v,
从u到v的最短路径中擦掉
and replace it with this shorter one.
然后将它替换为更短的路径
So, this is some hypothetical shorter path.
假设说这里有一些更短路径
So, suppose this existed. If that existed,
假设它存在 存在的话
then I should just cut the old path from x to y,
那么我只需要剪掉x到y的这段旧路径
and paste in this new one from x to y. It's strictly shorter.
然后将这条新路径粘贴上去 它绝对会更短
Therefore, I get a strictly shorter path from u to v.
因此 我得到了一条从u到v的更短的路径
But I assumed u to v was a shortest path: contradiction.
但我一开始就假设它是u到v的最短路径: 矛盾了
OK, so there is no shorter path.
所以 这里没有更短的路径
And that proves the lemma that we have this:
然后这里证明了一个引理
subpaths of shortest paths are shortest paths.
最短路径的子路径都是最短路径
OK, this should now be a pretty familiar proof technique.
现在这个证明技巧已经是我们的老友记了
But, there is yet another instance of cut and paste.
除此之外 还有别的剪切与粘贴的例子在等着我们
OK, so that's a good sign for computing shortest paths.
看来求出最短路径 已经指日可待了
I mean, in terms of dynamic programming,
我的意思是 就动态规划而言
we won't look directly at dynamic programming here because
我们不会直接对动态规划展开攻略
we are going to aim for greedy, which is even stronger.
因为我们要采用贪心策略 它更为强大
But, next Monday we'll see some dynamic programming approaches.
但在下周一 我们会看到动态规划的方法的
Intuitively, there are some pretty natural sub-problems here.
直观上看  这里很自然地会有一些子问题
I mean, going from u to v,
从u到v
if I want to find what is the shortest path from u to v,
当我想找从u到v的最短路径时
well, that's a particular problem.
这只是个特殊化的问题
Maybe it involves computing shortest paths
它可能包括了
from u to some intermediate point, x,
求从u到某个中间点x的最短路径
and then from x to u, something like that.
然后再从x到u的最短路径 诸如此类
That feels good.
挺带感嘛
That's like, quadratically, many subproblems.
这好像能分成很多子问题
And, V^2 subproblems,
V^2个子问题
it sounds like that would lead to a dynamic program.
感觉应该是往动态规划的方向走
You can make it work out;
你可以实现它
it's just a little bit trickier than that.
只不过要有点小技巧
We'll see that next Monday.
我们下周一会看到
But thinking about this intermediate point
但是现在想一下中间点
we get something called the triangle inequality.
我们知道有三角形不等式
So, you've probably heard some form of the triangle inequality before.
你们可能已经听说过三角形不等式的某些形式
It holds in all sorts of geometric spaces,
它在所有的几何空间内都是成立的
but it also holds for shortest paths,
对最短路径来说也是成立的
which is slightly less obvious, or more obvious,
可能不那么明显 也可能更明显
I guess, depending on your inclination.
可能跟倾角有关 我猜的
So, if you have any triple of vertices,
如果你有三个点
the shortest path from u to v is, at most,
从u到v的最短路径 最大不超过
the shortest path from u to x plus
u到x的最短路径加上
the shortest path from x to v.
x到v的最短路径
Of course, here I need a shortest path weight from u to x,
当然 我们需要知道 从u到x的最短路径的权值
and shortest path weight from x to v.
和从x到v的最短路径的权值
So, this should be pretty natural just from the statement,
这个命题看起来就相当顺理成章
even more natural if you draw the picture.
画个图出来的话 更加好理解
So, we have some vertex, u.
我们有个点u
I'm using wiggly lines to denote potentially long paths
我用曲线来表示那些可能更长的路径
as opposed to edges.
与边相对
We have some intermediate point, x,
我们有个中间点x
and we have some target, v,
还有个目的点v
and we are considering these three shortest paths.
然后我们考虑这三条最短路径
This is the shortest path from u to v,
这条是从u到v的最短路径
or this is its weights.
这是路径的权值
This is the shortest path from u to x, and here's its weight,
这里是u到x的最短路径和它的权值
And the shortest path from x to v, and here's its weight.
还有x到v的最短路径以及它的权值
And, the point is, well,
重点是
this should be the shortest path or a shortest path from u to v.
这应该是u到v的一条最短路径
And, in particular, one such path is you go from u to x,
特别的 这里有一条从u到x的路径
and then you go from x to v. So, I mean,
然后再从x到v 我的意思是
this sum is just measuring the length of this particular path.
这个和表示的是这一条路径的长度
Take the shortest path here; take the shortest path here.
这里一个最短路径 那里一个最短路径
And, this is supposed to be the Min over all paths.
而这一个 则是所有路径中的最小值
So, certainly this is, at most,
所以这当然不超过
this particular path, the sum of these two values,
这一条路径 这两个最短路径的和
OK, another proof by picture. Clear?
又一个图证 清楚了吗？
OK, this stuff is easy.
这个很简单
I assume we'll get into some more set exciting algorithms
我想很快 我们就要接触一些更有趣的算法了
in particular, which is always more exciting.
而且会是 相当意思的算法
Today, we're going to look at a particular version of shortest paths
今天 我们准备看看最短路径的一个特殊的版本
called, or the shortest paths problem
称为..或者说一种最短路径问题
called the single source shortest path problem.
叫作单源最短路径问题
OK, it's a little bit more general than go from A to B.
它比从A到B的定义要更广泛些
The problem is, you're given a source vertex,
问题是 给你一个顶点作为源点
and you want to know
你想要知道
how to get from that source vertex to everywhere else.
怎么从源顶点到达所有的点
So, we'll call this source vertex s.
好的 我们叫这个为源点S
And from that source, we want to find,
从源点出发 我们想找出
let's say, the shortest path weights from s to everyone.
从源点s 到其他所有点的最短路径
In particular, we'd also like to know the shortest paths,
尤其是 我们想知道最短路径是什么
but that isn't too much harder.
不过这并不会难很多
So, that's delta of s, v for all vertices, v.
那么 这是对于所有v求δ(s,v)
OK, so this is actually a little bit harder than
好吧 这个问题确实会难一点
the problem we started with a getting from Alderon to Cambridge.
相比于刚开始的从奥德隆到剑桥的问题来说
Now, we want to get from Alderon to the entire universe.
因为现在 我们想从奥德隆到全宇宙
OK, it turns out,
好吧 事实上
this is one of the weird things about shortest paths,
这也是最短路径的奇特之处之一
according to the state-of-the-art we know today,
根据我们当今的研究水平
it seems to be...it seems like the following statement
好像...接下来的命题看起来
will remain true for all time. But we don't know.
总会是成立的 但也可能是真实的谎言
The best algorithms for solving the A to B problem——
解决A到B最短路径问题的最佳算法——
given s, given t, go from s to t,
已知s和t 从s到t
——is no easier than this problem.
——不会比这个问题简单
It's the best ways we know how to solve going from A to B
我们所知道的 求A到B最短路径的最佳算法
is to solve how to go from A to everywhere else.
就是求从A到任意地方的最短路径
So, we sort of can't help ourselves,
好像除了这么做以外
but to solve this problem it turns out.
也没什么更好的办法了
Today, we're going to look at a further restriction on this problem
今天 我们要给这个问题加一些限制条件
because this is a bit tricky.
因为这儿有点小技巧
We'll solve it next class.
剩下的我们留到下次课
But, today we're going to get rid of
但是 今天我们先不管
the negative weight cycle issue
负权值环的问题
by forbidding negative weights.
所以禁止负权值的存在
So, we're going to assume that
所以 我们先假设
all of the edge weights are nonnegative,
所有的边都是非负的
so, for all vertices, u and v.
对于所有的u和v
So, in particular,
也就是说
shortest paths exist, provided paths exist.
最短路径存在 只要路径存在
And, we don't have to worry about these minus infinities.
那么我们就不用担心负无穷的情况
Delta of (u,v) is always bigger than minus infinity.
δ(u,v)总是大于负无穷
It still might be plus infinity if there is no path,
虽然没有路径的话 还会有正无穷的情况
but this will make life a lot easier.
但至少能给我们省点脑细胞
And the algorithm we'll cover today really requires this property.
我们今天讲的这个算法真的很依赖这个条件
You can't get away without it.
没它不行
Next class, we'll get away without it
下节课 我们就可以去掉这个条件
with a fancier and slower algorithm.
用一个酷炫但较慢的算法
So, as I hinted at,
之前剧透过了
the main idea we're going to use for the algorithm today is greedy,
我们今天的算法思想是 贪心
which should be faster than dynamic programming generally
它一般比动态规划要快
And, the tricky part will be
但有技巧的部分是
proving that the greedy algorithm actually works.
如何证明贪心算法确实有效
So, I think there's pretty much only one natural way to go about,
所以 我觉得大概只有一种合适的方法来证明
there's one way that works to go about greedy, let's say
可能只有一种方法适合贪心算法
This may be not the obvious one.
但这可能不容易想得到
So, let me give you a little bit of setup.
我先给你们一些前提条件
The invariant we are going to maintain
我们要维持一个不变量
is that at all times, we have
在任意时刻 我们都要
estimates on the distances from the source to every vertex
估算从源点到每个点的距离
When I say distance, I mean shortest path weight.
我所说的距离 指的是最短路径的权值
I'm going to use weight and distance interchangeably here
我说的权值和距离可以互换的
for more intuition.
听起来更顺耳
And, in particular, I want to maintain the set of vertices
而且 我还想要维持那些
where those estimates are actually the right answer.
估算距离已经是最短距离的顶点
OK, this is little s. This is big S. So,
这个是小写s 这个是大写S
the big S will be the set of all vertices where I know the answer.
大写S是所有已知最短路径的顶点的集合
What is the shortest path distance
小写s到大写S集合中每个点
from little s to that vertex in big S?
最短距离分别是多少？
So, for starters, which distance do I know?
一开始时 我们知道的是哪些距离？
Sorry? s.
没听清？s
I know the shortest path distance from s to s
我知道的是s到s的最短距离
because if I assume that all of my weights are nonnegative,
因为前提是所有边的权值都是非负的
I really can't get from s to s any faster than not doing anything.
啥都不做总要比有任何动作都要快吧
OK, if I had a negative weight cycle, maybe
好吧 如果有负环的话 可能不一样
the distance from s to s is minus infinity.
s到s的距离等于负无穷
OK, but I can't have negative weights
好的 但是我没有负权值
so there's no way I can get from s to s any faster than zero time.
所以这里我没法比0还要更快
There might be a longer path that still has zero cost,
可能有条路绕多几个点 但费用还是0
but it can't be any better than zero.
不过没有比0更快的了
So, in particular, I know that.
所以 我知道
So, initially, S is certainly an s.
一开始S里面肯定有一个s
OK, and the idea is we're going to
好的 按这种思路 我们要
accumulate more and more vertices that we know.
不断地增加我们已知的点
So, at some point we know the distances from some of the vertices.
某种程度上 我们知道到某些点的距离
So, we have some cloud here.
我们这里有一堆东西
This is S, and this is everything else.
这是S 然后这是其他的东西
This is the graph, G.
这个就是图G
This is the subset of the vertices.
这个是顶点的子集合
And, there's some edges that go out from there.
然后这些是从集合S里连出来的边
And, so we have estimates on how to get to these vertices.
我们有 到外面一些点的距离估算
Some of them, we may not have even seen yet.
但其中一些点 我们可能无法得知
They may not be connected to this portion of S.
它们可能没有跟S里的点相连
I mean: not directly.
我是指：无法直连
They might be connected by some longer path.
可能要通过更长的路才能相连
They might be in a completely different connected component.
它们可能处于完全不同的连通分量里
We don't know yet.
我们暂时不知道
Some of them, we have estimates for
我们已经估算出它们其中一部分
because we've sort of seen how to get there from S.
因为我们已经知道怎么从连到那儿了
And the idea is,
然后 思路是
among all of these nodes where we have estimates,
在这些已经估算好的点之中
and on to get from little S,
然后从小写s出发的
which is some vertex in here, to these vertices,
也就是里面的某个点 到外面的这些点
we're going to take the one for which the estimate is smallest.
我们准备取它们中距离最小的那个
That's the greedy choice.
这就是贪心的策略
And, we're just going to add that vertex to S.
然后 我们就把那一点加入到S中
So, S grows one vertex per step.
那么 S每一步都增加一个点
Each step, we're going to add to S, the vertex.
每一步 我们加到S的点
Of course, again, this is not a unique,
当然 可能不止一个点
it's a vertex, v, in V minus S.
它是一个点v 在V减S的集合中
So, it's something we haven't yet computed yet
所以 这是一个还没经过验算的...
whose estimated distance from S is minimum.
离S的距离最短的点
So, we look at all the vertices we haven't yet added to S.
所以 我们观察所有还没加进S的点
Just take the one where we have the estimated smallest distance.
然后从中选出距离最小的一个点
The intuition is that that should be a good choice.
直觉告诉我 这是一个好的选择
So, if I pick the one that's closest to little s
如果我选的这一个离小s最近
among all the ones that I've seen,
在所有我看到的顶点之中
among all the paths that I've seen,
在所有我看到的路径之中
I sort of have to buy into that those are good paths.
我会认为这样能选出好的路径
But, I mean, maybe there's some path I didn't see.
但是 我想说 可能还有些我们没看到的路径
Maybe you go out to here
或者当你走到这儿
and then you take some other path to some vertex,
然后你另选一条新路径
which we've already seen.
去一个曾经看过的点
OK, the worry is, well,
好的 我们担心
I'd better not say that that's the shortest path
这个可能并不是最短路径
because there may have been some other way to get there.
因为可能有别的路径能到那儿去
Right, as soon as I add something to S, I declare
好的 当我往S里加入某个点 我就说
I've solved the problem for that vertex.
关于这个点的问题已经解决了
I can't change my answer later.
我后面不会再改动它了
OK, the estimates can change until they get added to S.
在被加入到S之前 估算距离可能会变
So, I don't want to add this vertex to S
所以 我不想把这个点加到S中
because I haven't considered this path.
因为我还没考虑过这条路径
Well, if all my weights are nonnegative,
那么 如果权值是非负的话
and I take the vertex here that has the shortest estimate from S,
然后 我选取离S估算距离最短的点
so let's suppose this one is the shortest one,
让我们假设这个是最短路径
then this can't be a shorter path
那这条路就不可能比它更短
because the distance estimate, at least, from S to that vertex
因为S到这个顶点的估算距离 至少
is larger from S to that vertex.
要比S到那个点的大
So, no way can I make the path longer and decrease the distance.
所以 不可能路绕远了 距离反而短了
That's the intuition.
这是直觉的推断
OK, it's a little bit fuzzy here
好的 这个地方有点混乱
because I don't have any induction hypotheses set up,
因为我没有建立任何归纳假设
and it's going to be a lot more work to prove that.
而且要证明它 好像要花很多功夫
But that's the intuition why this is the right thing to do.
但这个推断说明这个方法是行的
You have to prove something about the distance estimates for that
你还需要对估算距离证明一些东西
to be a proof.
来证明它是可行的
But, intuitively, it feels good.
但根据剧情发展 这肯定是可行的
It was a good starting point.
至少这个开局还挺顺的
And then presumably we have to maintain these distance estimates.
可想而知 我们需要维护这些估算的距离
So, the heart of the algorithm is updating distance estimates,
这个算法的核心就是更新估算距离
I mean, choosing the best vertex to add to S, that's one step.
我是说 选出最好的点加入到S中 这是第一步
Then, updating the distance estimates is
然后 更新估算距离
is sort of where the work is.
这是最主要的一步
And, it turns out
事实上
we'll only need to update distance estimates of some of the vertices,
我们只需要更新某些点的估算距离
the ones that are adjacent to v.
就那些与v相连的点
v was the vertex we just added to S.
v是指 刚刚加进S中的顶点
So, once we add somebody to S,
一旦我们往S里加入某些点
so we grow S by a little bit,
S就扩大了一点点
then we look at all the new edges that go out of S.
然后我们观察最新连入S的那些边
From that vertex, we update something.
那个顶点连什么 我们就更新什么
That's the idea.
这就是主要思路
So, that's the idea for how we're going to use greedy.
这就是怎么运用贪心策略的思路
Now I'll give you the algorithm.
现在我给出这个算法
So, this is called Dijkstra's algorithm.
它的名字叫Dijkstra算法
Dijkstra is a famous, recently late,
Dijkstra是近代著名的
if that makes sense, computer scientist from the Netherlands.
计算机科学家 来自荷兰 如果没记错的话
And, this is probably the algorithm he is most famous for.
而且 这个可能是他最著名的算法
So, the beginning of the algorithm is just some initialization,
这个算法一开始只是初始化
not too exciting.
没什么特别
OK, but let me tell you what some of the variables mean.
好的 我先来告诉你们这些变量代表什么
OK, so d is some array indexed by vertices,
好的 d是一个以顶点为下标的数组
and the idea is that d of x is the distance estimate for x,
而d[x]则是起点到x的距离的估算距离
so, from S to x. So in particular,
也就是从s到x 而且
it's going to equal the real shortest path weight from S to x
它将会是从s到x的真正的最短路径权值
when we've added x to our set capital, S.
仅当我们把x加入到大写S集合中时
OK, so this is, in particular,
好的 也就是说
going to be the output to the algorithm.
这就是这个算法的输出结果
Did you have a question?
你在举手提问吗？
Or were you just stretching? Good.
噢 原来你是奥特曼同学
So, in d of x, when we are done, d of x is the output.
所以 当我们完成时 d[x]就是输出
For every vertex, it's going to give us
对于每个顶点 它最后都会给出
the shortest path weight from S to that vertex.
从S到那个顶点的最短路径的权重
Along the way,
一路下来
it's going to be some estimated distance from S to that vertex.
它都是从S到某一点的估算距离
And, we're going to improve it over time.
然后 我们每次都更新它
This is an infinity.
这个等于正无穷
So initially, we know that the distance,
一开始时 我们知道这个距离等于..
we know the distance from s to s is zero.
点s到点s的距离为0
So, we're going to set that to be our estimate.
我们把它作为估算距离
It's going to be accurate.
虽然肯定是对的
Everything else we're going to just set to infinity
其他的点 我们只需要设为正无穷
because we may not be connected.
因为它们跟s可能不相连
From the beginning, we don't know much.
刚开始时 我们知道得不多
S, initially, is going to be infinity.
S一开始是正无穷
Immediately, we're going to add little s to big S.
马上 我们就往S里加入小写s
And then, the interesting part here is Q,
然后 最有趣的是这里有个Q
which is going to consist of,
Q将会包括有
initially all the vertices in the graph.
一开始是图中所有的点
And, it's going to not just be a queue as the letter suggests.
这个Q不单说明了它是队列Queue
It's going to be a priority queue.
它还是一个优先队列
So, it's going to maintain, in particular,
特别地 它还要维护...
the vertex that has the smallest distance estimate.
有着最小估算距离的顶点
So, this is a priority queue.
那么 它是一个优先队列
This is really an abuse of notation for a data structure.
这个确实是数据结构符号的滥用
OK, so this could be a heap or whatever.
好吧 这个可能是一个堆什么的
The vertices are keyed on d, our distance estimate.
这些顶点以d为键 也就是估算距离
So, in particular,
注意一点
S will have the, this is going to be a Min heap.
S会有...这应该是一个最小堆
S will be the guy who has the minimum.
S将要获得那个最小的值
Everyone else has the same key initially.
一开始每个人的键都相同
And, we're going to repeatedly
然后 我们不断地
extract the minimum element from this queue and do other things.
从这队列中取出最小值 然后做下一步
OK, so this is initialization.
好的 这就是初始化
OK, I'm going to call that initialization.
好的 然后我进行初始化
It's a pretty simple thing.
相当简单的东西
It just takes linear time, nothing fancy going on.
只需要线性时间 没有什么特别
The heart of the algorithm is all in six lines.
这个算法的核心全在这六行里
And, so this is not really a step.
这实际上还不算一步
The first step here that we need to do is
我们要做的第一步是
we take the vertex whose distance estimate is minimum.
我们取出估算距离最小的顶点
So that, among all the vertices, not yet,
所以 在所有顶点中....
and that's currently S is empty. Q has everyone.
当前的S为空集 Q有所有顶点
In general, Q will have everyone except S.
一般来说 Q有除S外的所有顶点
So, we'll take the vertex, u,
那么 我们取顶点u
that has the minimum key in that priority queue.
它对应优先队列里 键值最小的顶点
So, extract the Min from Q.
所以 从Q中取出最小值
We're going to add a little u to S,
我们把u加入S中
claim that that is now,
我们说 现在有
I mean, that's exactly what we're saying here.
我指的是 就像我们这里讲的那样
We add to S that vertex that has minimum distance estimate.
我们往S里加入估算距离最小的顶点
And now, we need to update the distances.
而现在 我们需要更新估算距离
So, we're going to look at each adjacent vertex
我们观察所有跟u邻接的点
for each v in the adjacency list for u.
在u的邻接表里的每个顶点v
We look at a few distances.
我们要更新这些距离
So that's the algorithm or more or less.
这个算法差不多就是这样
This is the key.
这个是键值
I should define it a little bit what's going on here.
我应该说明下这里发生了什么
We talked mainly about undirected graph last time.
我们上次主要说了无向图
Here, we're thinking about directed graphs.
这里 我们考虑一下有向图
And, the adjacency list for u here is just going to mean,
然后这个u的邻接表 它表示的是
give me all the vertices for which there is an edge from u to v.
给出从u到v有边相连的所有顶点v
So, this is the outgoing adjacency list,
所以 这就是连出的邻接表
not the incoming adjacency list.
而不是连入的邻接表
Undirected graphs: you list everything.
在无向图里 你要列出所有东西
Directed graphs: here, we're only going to care about those ones.
有向图里 我们只需要关心那一些
So, for every edge, (u,v), is what this is saying,
所以对于每一条边(u,v) 也就是这个
we are going to compare the current estimate for v,
我们要拿v当前的估算距离
and this candidate estimate,
和这个候选的估算值比较
which intuitively means you go from s to u.
说白了就是 你先从s到达了u
That's d of u because we now know that that's the right answer.
路程是d[u] 因为我们已知正确答案了
This, in fact, equals,
这个实际上等于
we hope, assuming the algorithm is correct,
我们先假设这个算法是正确的
this should be the shortest path weight from s to u
这应该就是从s到u 最短路径的权值
because we just added u to S.
因为我们把u加进了S中
And whenever we add something to S, it should have the right value.
每当我们往S里加入某些东西 它就应该是最小的值
So, we could say, well,
所以 我们说
you take the shortest path from S to u,
你先从S选最短的路径到达u
and then you follow this edge from u to v.
然后你再顺着从u到v的边走
That has weight, w, of (u,v).
(u,v)的权值为w
That's one possible path from S to v.
这就是从S到达v的一条可能的路径
And, if that's a shorter path
如果这一条路径
than the one we currently have in our estimate,
比当前集合中的估算距离更短话
if this is smaller than that,
如果这个比那个要小
then we should update the estimate to be that sum
那我们就应该把估算值更新为那个和
because that's a better path,
因为这条路径更好
so, add it to our database of paths, so to speak:
然后 把它加入我们路径的集合中
OK, very intuitive operation;
好的 很直观的操作
clearly should not do anything bad.
很明显这样做没有错
I mean, these should be paths that makes sense.
我的意思是 选这条路是有道理的
We'll prove that in a moment.
我们待会儿再证明
That's the first part of correctness, that this never screws up.
这是成功的第一步 而它从不出错
And then, the tricky part is
然后 巧妙的地方是
to show that it finds all the paths that we care about.
要证明这样能把我们所要的所有路径找出来
This step is called a relaxation step.
这一步的操作叫作松弛
Relaxation is always a difficult technique to teach to MIT students.
要教MIT的孩子学松弛总是很困难
It doesn't come very naturally.
这方法并不是那么的自然
But it's very simple operation.
但它是一个非常简单的操作
It comes from optimization terminology,
它来自最优化方法的一个术语
programming terminology, so to speak.
也可说是一个编程术语
And, does this inequality look familiar at all
这条不等式看起来是不是很眼熟？
especially when you start writing it this way?
尤其是当你写成这种形式的时候?
You say, the shortest path from S to v
你说 这个从S到v的最短路径
and the shortest path from S to u in some edge from u to v,
和S到u最短路径 再走u到v的边
does that look like anything we've seen?
是不是似曾相似?
In fact, it was on this board but I just erased it.
实际上 它刚刚还写在黑板上 后来被我擦掉了
Triangle inequality, yeah.
三角形不等式 对了
So, this is trying to make the triangle inequality true.
所以 这就是想要让三角形不等式成立
Certainly, the shortest path from S to v
当然 S到v的最短路径
should be less than or equal to, not greater than.
应该小于等于 也就是不大于
The shortest path from S to u,
S到u的最短路径
plus whatever path from u to v,
加上u到v的任意路径
this shortest path should be, at most, that.
这个最短路径不大于右边的
So, this is sort of a somewhat more general triangle inequality.
所以 这是一条更广义的三角形不等式
And, we want to, certainly it should be true.
然后我们想...当然它是真的
So, if it's not true, we fix it.
如果不成立的话 我们就修正它
If it's greater than, we make it equal.
如果它大于右边 我们令它相等
But we don't want to make it less than
但不会令它小于右边
because that's not always true.
因为这不一定成立
OK, but certainly, it should be less than or equal to.
但肯定 它应该小于等于右边
So, this is fixing the triangle inequality.
这个就是修正三角形不等式
It's trying to make that constraint more true.
要让这个约束条件变得更可靠
In optimization, that's called relaxing the constraint.
在最优化方法里 这样称为对约束的松弛
OK, so we're sort of relaxing the triangle inequality here.
好的 我们要对这个三角形不等式进行松弛
Over and over and over.
一次 一次 又一次
By the end, we should have all the shortest paths.
到最后 我们会得出所有的最短路径
That's a claim. So, a very simple algorithm.
这是一个断言 好的 非常简单的算法
Let's try it out on a graph,
我们在图上实测一下
and that should make it more intuitive why it's working,
这样能更直白地解释 它为什么有用
and that the rest of the lecture will be proving that it works.
剩下的课 就是要证明它是有用的
Yeah, this is enough room.
好的 够地方写了
So, oh, I should mention one other thing here. Sorry.
那么..我还要提到另外一样东西 不好意思
Whenever we change d of v,
每当我改变d[v]
this is changing the key of v in the priority queue.
这是在改变v在优先队列里对应的键值
So, implicitly what's happening here in this assignment,
所以 这条赋值语句也意味着
this is getting a bit messy,
这写得有点乱
is a decreased key operation,
它是一个降低键值的操作
OK, which we talked briefly about last class
好的 我们上一节课简单讲过
in the context of minimum spanning trees
就在讲最小生成树的时候
where we were also decreasing the key.
当时也是要降低键值
The point is we were changing the key of one element
重点是要在这个优先队列的松弛操作中
in this relaxation step in the priority queue
降低某个对应元素的键值
so that if it now becomes the minimum, we should extract here
所以如果它变成了最小值 下一个取出的就是它
And, we are only ever decreasing keys because
而且 我们只会降低键值
we are always replacing larger values with smaller values.
因为我们总是用大数 来替换小数
So, we'll come back to that later when we analyze the running time.
那么 稍后分析运行时间时 我们会再讨论它
But, there is some data structure work going on here.
但这儿又有一些数据结构的问题
Again, we are abusing notation a bit.
我们又在滥用符号了
OK, so here is a graph with edge weights.
好的 这里有个带权值的图
OK, and I want my priority queue over here.
好的 这里是我的优先队列
And, I'm also going to draw my estimates.
然后 我也把估算距离画出来
OK, now I don't want to cheat.
好的 我不想作假
So, we're going to run the algorithm on this graph.
那么 我们要在这个图上运行这个算法
s will be A,
s就是A
and I want to know the shortest path from A to everyone else.
然后 我想知道A到任意一点的最短距离
So, you can check, OK, paths exist.
好的 你看到 路径是存在的
So, hopefully everything should end up a finite value by the end.
所以 每个点都应该得到一个有限的值
All the weights are nonnegative,
所有的权值都是非负的
so this algorithm should work.
所以 这个算法应该有用
The algorithm doesn't even need connectivity,
这个算法甚至不要求连通性
but it does mean that all the weights are nonnegative.
但是它要求每个权值都是非负的
So, we run the algorithm.
那么 我们运行这个算法
For the initialization,
在初始化过程中
we set the distance estimate for our source to be zero because,
我们设起点的距离等于0
in fact, there's only one path from A to A,
因为实际上 从A到A只有一条路径
and that to do nothing, the empty path.
那就是不用走 空路径
So, I'm going to put the key of zero over here.
所以我要设它的键值为零
And, for everyone else,
然后 对于其他每个顶点
we're just going to put infinity because
我们都设为正无穷
we don't know any better at this point.
因为这时 我们不知道怎么到那里
So, I'll put keys of infinity for everyone else.
所以 我会设其它的键值全为∞
OK, so now you can see what the algorithm does
好的 现在你看到这个算法要做的就是..
is extract the minimum from the queue.
从队列中取出最小值
And, given our setup, we'll definitely choose s,
然后 根据已知设定 我们当然会选择s
or in this case, A.
在例子里就是A
So, it has a weight of zero.
所以 它的权值就等于0
Everyone else has quite a bit larger weight.
其它的每个点的权值都比它大
OK, so we look at s, or I'll use A here.
好的 我们观察s 或者这里用A表示
So, we look at A. We add A to our set, S.
我们观察A 我们把A加到集合S中
So, I'm going to square something when it...
我用个框框来做标记
It's now removed from the queue or never go back in
它现在从队列中移除了 不会再回去了
because we never add anything to the queue,
因为我们从来不会向队列里加任何东西
start with all the vertices,
它一开始就有所有顶点
and extract, and decrease keys.
我们只会提取最小值和降低键值
But we never insert. So, A is gone.
但是我们从不插入 所以A不在了
OK, and now I want to update the keys
好的 现在我们想要更新
of all of the other vertices.
所有其他顶点的键值
And the claim is I only need to
那么我只要
look at the vertices that have edges from A.
观察那些跟A有边连着的点
So, there's an edge from A to B,
好的 从A到B有条边
and that has weight ten.
它的权值等于10
And so, I compare:
然后我就比较
well, is it a good idea to go from A to A, which costs nothing,
好的 从A到A是一个好选择 因为没有任何花费
and then to go along this edge, AB, which costs ten?
然后沿着AB边走  费用为10
Well, it seems like a pretty good idea because
好的 看上去还不错
that has a total weight of zero plus ten, which is ten,
因为它的总权值等于0+10 也就是10
which is much smaller than infinity.
比正无穷要小得多
So, I'm going to erase this infinity;
所以 我要擦掉这个无穷
write ten, and over in the queue as well.
写上10 在队列里也改掉
That's the decreased key operation.
这就是降低键值的操作
So now, I know a path from A to B. Good.
而现在 我知道A到B之间有一条路径 好
A to C is the only other edge.
从A到C是另外一条边
Zero plus three is less than infinity,
0+3小于无穷大
So, cool. I'll put three here for C, and C is there.
很好 我给C写一个3 C在这里
OK, the other vertices I don't touch.
好的 另外一些顶点我没访问过
I'm going to rewrite them here,
我把它们重新写一遍
but the algorithm doesn't have to copy them.
但在算法里 我们并不用复制它
Those keys were already there.
这些键值已经在那里了
It's just touching these two.
我们只接触到这两个点
OK, that was pretty boring.
好吧 这会有点无聊
Now we look at our queue, and we extract the minimum element.
现在我们观察我们的队列 然后提取最小值
So, A is no longer in there,
A已经不在里面了
so the minimum key here is three.
所以 这里的最小值是3
So, the claim is that this is a shortest path; from A to C,
所以 说明这里的最短路径是：从A到C
here is the shortest path from A to C.
这是从A到C的最短路径
There's no other shorter way.
没有别的更短的路径了
You could check that, and we'll prove it in a moment.
你们先记一下 我们过会儿再证明它
Cool, so we'll remove C from the list. It's gone.
很好 我们从列表上删除C 它不在了
Then we look at all of the outgoing edges from C.
然后 我们看到所有从C出来的边
So, there's one that goes up to B,
这里有一条是到B的
which has weight four, four plus three,
权值为4 4加上3
which is the shortest path weight from A to C.
3是从A到C的最短路径
So, going from A to C, and C to B
所以从A到C 从C到B
should cost three plus four,
这些费用为3加4
which is seven, which is less than ten.
也就是7 比10要小
So, we found an even better path to get to B.
所以 我们发现从这条路径到B会更好
It's better to go like this than it is to go like that.
它这么走 比它那么走要好
So, we write seven for B,
所以 我们给B写上7
and there's an outgoing edge from C to D which costs eight.
这里还有一条从C到D 费用为8的边
Three plus eight is 11.
3加上8等于11
11 is less than infinity, as I checked.
11小于正无穷 很显然
So, we write 11 for D. Then we look at E.
所以 我们给D一个11 然后我们观察E
We have three plus two is five,
我们有3所加2等于5
which is less than infinity.
小于正无穷
So, we write five for the new key for E.
所以 E的新键值为5
At this point, we have finite shortest paths to everywhere,
到现在 所有顶点都有一条有限的路径相连了
but they may not be the best ones.
但它们可能不是最好的那个
So, we have to keep looking.
所以 我们继续观察
OK, next round of the algorithm,
好的 算法的下一轮里
we extract the minimum key among all these.
我们再从这里取出最小值
OK, it's not B, which we've seen though probably know the answer to.
好的 不是B 我们都已经知道答案是什么了
But it's E. E has the smallest key.
它是E E的键值最小
So, we now declare this to be a shortest path.
现在 我们宣称这是最短路径
The way we got to E was...along this path:
我们到达E的方法是 沿着这条路径
A to C, C to E, declare that to be shortest.
A到C C到E 我们称这是最短的
We claim we're done with E.
我们说我们搞定E了
But we still have to update.
但是 我们还要继续更新
What about all the outgoing edges from E?
哪些是从E点出发的边？
There's only one here.
这里只有一条
It costs five plus nine, which is 14,
它的费用是5+9 等于14
which is bigger than 11.
比11要大
So, no go. That's not an interesting path.
所以不走这里 这不是我们想要的
Our previous path, which went like this at a cost of the 11,
之前的路径 它是这么走 费用为11
is better than the one we are considering now.
比我们正在考虑这条的要好
I'm drawing the whole path,
我画出了这整条路径
but the algorithm is only adding these two numbers.
但这个算法只需要把这两个数加起来
OK, good. So, I don't change anything.
好的 我什么都不用改
Seven, 11, and five is removed, or E is removed.
剩下7和11  5也就是E被删除了
Our new keys are seven and 11.
我们新的键值是7和11
So, we take the key, seven, here,
所以 我们取出7
which is for element B, vertex B.
也就是顶点B
We declare the path we currently have in our hands from A to B,
我们称现在从A到B的最短路径...
which happens to be this one.
刚好是这一条
Algorithm can't actually tell this, by the way,
这个算法实际上不会告诉你
but we're drawing it anyway.
但我们还是把它画出来吧
This path, A, C, B, is the candidate shortest path.
这条路径A C B 是候选的最短路径
The claim is it is indeed shortest.
它事实上就是最短的
Now, we look at all the outgoing edges.
现在我们观察这些所有向外连的边
There's one that goes back to C at a cost of seven plus one,
这里有一条边走回C 费用为7加1
which is eight, which is bigger than three, which is good.
等于8 比3要大 好的
We already declared C to be done.
我们已经可以说C也搞定了
But the algorithm checks this path and says,
但是这个算法还是会检查 然后说
oh, that's no better.
哦 没有更好的了
And then we look at this other edge from B to D.
接着我们观察B到D的这条边
That costs seven plus two, which is nine,
费用为7加2 等于9
which is better than 11.
比11要好
So, we, in fact, found an even shorter path.
所以 我们其实找到了一条更短的路径
So, the shortest path weight, now, for D, is nine
所以 当前D的最短路径的权值是9
because there is this path that goes A, C, B, D
因为这条经A C B D的路径
for a total cost of three plus four plus two is nine.
总费用为3+4+2=9
Cool, now there's only one element in the queue.
爽啊 现在队列里只剩下一个元素
We remove it.
我们移除它
d: we look at the outgoing edges.
D 我们观察这些向外的边
There's one going here which costs nine plus seven,
这条的费用是9+7
which is 16, which is way bigger than five.
等于16 比5要大
So, we're done. Don't do anything.
所以 完成了 什么都不用干
At this point, the queue is empty.
这个时候 队列是空的
And the claim is that all these numbers that are written here,
我们说 所有写在这里的数字
the final values are the shortest path weights.
最终的值就是最短路径的权值
This looks an awful lot like a five, but it's an s.
它看起来超级像5 其实它是s
It has a weight of zero.
它的权值等于0
I've also drawn in here all the shortest paths.
我这里也画出了所有最短路径
And, this is not hard to do.
这个不难
We're not going to talk about it too much in this class,
关于这个 我们这次课不会讲太多
but it's mentioned in a little bit more detail in the textbook.
书上面会讲得更清楚
And it's something called the shortest path tree.
它叫做最短路径树
It's just something good to know about
当你真的想求出最短路径时
if you actually want to compute shortest paths.
它确实值得你去了解
In this class, we mainly worry about the weights
这节课里面 我们主要关心的是权值
because it's pretty much the same problem.
因为它差不多都是一样的问题
The shortest path tree is the union of all shortest paths.
最短路径树就是所有最短路径的集合
And in particular, if you look at each vertex in your graph,
尤其是 当你观察图中的每个点时
and you consider the last edge into that vertex
你考虑到所有的点u中
that was relaxed among all vertices, u,
最后一条被松弛的边
you look at the edges, (u,v),
看到这条边(u,v)
say, was that last one to relax?
只要问 这是最后被松弛的边吗？
So, just look at the last edges we relaxed here.
那么 只需要留意最后一条被松弛的边
You put them all together: that's called a shortest path tree.
把它们放在一起 这就叫做最短路径树
And, it has the property that from S to everywhere else,
它有一个性质就是从s出发到所有的点
there is a unique path down the tree.
从根到叶的路径是唯一的
And it's the shortest path.
而且是最短路径
It's the shortest path that we found.
它就是我们要找的最短路径
OK, so you actually get shortest paths out of this algorithm
实际上 你已经用这算法找到了所有最短路径
even though it's not explicitly described.
尽管它没有显式地说明是哪一条
All we are mainly talking about are the shortest path weights.
但我们主要讨论的是最短路径的权
Algorithm clear at this point?
现在这个算法都清楚吗？
Feels like it's doing the right thing?
都觉得它不水吧？
You can check all those numbers are the best paths.
你可以验证下 所有数字都是最佳的路径
And now we're going to prove that.
现在我们准备去证明它
So: correctness.
它的正确性
So the first thing I want to prove is that
那第一件我要证明的事情是
relaxation never makes a mistake.
松弛操作是不会出错的
If it ever sets d of v to be something,
如果它设d[v]为某值
I want to prove that d of v is always an upper bound on delta.
我想证明d[v]总是δ的一个上界
So, we have this invariant.
所以 我们有一个不变式
D[v] greater than or equal to delta of s, v for all v.
对于所有v d[v]大于等于δ(s,v)
And, this invariant holds at all times.
这个不变式总是成立的
So, after initialization,
在初始化以后
it doesn't hold before initialization
初始化之前 它并不成立
because d isn't defined then.
因为那时d还没被定义好
But if you do this initialization where you set S to zero,
而初始化就是将s设为0
and everyone else to infinity,
其它的设为正无穷
and you take any sequence of relaxation steps,
然后你进行任意一个松弛操作
then this variant will hold after each relaxation step you apply.
每一步松弛后 这个不变式都成立
This is actually a very general lemma.
这其实是非常普通的引理
It's also pretty easy to prove.
而且很容易证明
It holds not only for Dijkstra's algorithm,
不仅仅对Dijkstra算法来说是成立的
but for a lot of other algorithms we'll see.
对许多别的算法也是成立的
Pretty much every algorithm we see will involve relaxation.
我们将会接触到许多带有松弛操作的算法
And, this is saying no matter what relaxations you do,
而这就是说 无论你做了什么松弛操作
you always have a reasonable estimate in the sense that
你的估算总是合理的 那是因为
it's greater than or equal to the true shortest path weight.
它总会大于或等于最短路径的权重
So, it should be converging from above.
那么 它应该可以从上往下收敛
So, that's the lemma. Let's prove it.
我们来证明这个引理
Any suggestions on how we should prove this lemma?
你们有什么好点子来证明这个引理？
What technique might we use?
可以用到什么技巧？
What's that? Cut and paste?
什么？ 剪贴法？
It would be good for optimal substructure.
这个对最优子结构有用
Cut and paste: maybe sort of what's going on here
剪贴法 好像跟这儿有点关系
but not exactly.
但不确切是
Something a little more general.
要更加广义一点的东西
It's just intuition here;
这只是测测人品
it doesn't have to be the right answer.
不一定要给出正确答案
In fact, many answers are correct,
实际上 很多答案都是对的
have plausible proofs.
有各种合理的证明
Induction, yeah.
数学归纳 对了
So, I'm not going to write induction here,
那么 我不会特地写上数学归纳
but effectively we are using induction.
但实际上 我们用的是数学归纳
That's the answer I was expecting.
这个是我们一直期待的答案
So, there is sort of an induction already in time going on here.
其实 这就差不多是归纳法了
We say after initialization it should be true.
我们说 在初始化之后 这个应该为真
That's our base case.
这是我们的基础命题
And then, every relaxation we do, it should still be true.
接下来 每一次松弛之后 它仍然为真
So, we're going to assume by induction that
我们用归纳来假设
all the previous relaxations worked,
前面的松弛都起效了
and then we're going to prove that the last relaxation,
我们来证明 这个最后的松弛
whatever it is, works.
无论如何都是有效的
So, first let's do the base case.
我们先看基础命题
So, this is after an initialization,
这个是初始化之后
let's say, initially.
一开始...
So, initially we have d of s equal to zero.
一开始我们有d[s]等于0
And we have d of v equal to infinity for all other vertices,
对于其它的顶点v d[v]为正无穷
for all vertices, v, not equal to little s.
所有的顶点v 除了s以外
OK, now we have to check that this inequality holds.
好的 我们得要检查这个不等式是否成立
Well, we have delta of s, s.
我们有δ(s,s)
We've already argued that that's zero.
我们已经讨论过这个为0
You can't get negative
你没法得到负值
when there are only nonnegative edge weights.
因为这里只有非负权值的边
So, that's the best.
那么 这样是最好的
So, certainly zero is greater than or equal to zero.
0是大于等于0的
And, we have everything else,
然后 我们还有其它全部
well, I mean, delta of S, v
我的意思是 δ(s,v)
is certainly less than or equal to infinity.
肯定是小于等于正无穷
So this holds.
这个是成立的
Everything is less than or equal to infinity.
每一个数都是小于等于正无穷的
So: base case is done.
基础命题就这样
So, now we do an induction.
现在我们进行归纳
And, I'm going to write it as a proof by contradiction.
那么 我准备用反证法来证明它
So, let's say,
那么 我们有——
suppose that this fails to hold at some point.
假设这个对某些点来说是不成立的
So, suppose for contradiction that the invariant is violated.
假设这个不变式在某时候是不成立的
So, we'd like to sue the violator and find a contradiction.
我们要指证这个反例有矛盾
So, it's going to be violated.
那么 它是不成立的
So, let's look at the first violation,
我们看看第一个出错地方
the first time it's violated.
第一次它出错时
So, this is, essentially, again, a proof by induction.
实际上 这又是一个数学归纳法的证明
So, let's say we have some violation,
当第一次违反不变式的时候
d of v is less than delta of s, v. That would be bad
d[v]<δ(s,v) 这就糟糕了
If we somehow got an estimate smaller than the shortest path
如果估算距离比最短路径更小的时候
Well, then I think about looking at the first violation is
呃 我在想这是第一次出错
we know sort of by induction that all other values are correct.
根据归纳假设 之前其它的值都应该是对的
OK, d of v is the first one where we've screwed up.
好 d[v]就是第一个我们出错的地方
So, the invariant holds everywhere else.
那么 这个不变式在哪里都是成立的
Well, what caused this to fail,
导致它出错的
this invariant to be violated, is some relaxation,
使不变式不成立的 是某步松弛操作
OK, on d of v.
好的 对于d[v]
So, we had some d of v,
我们有个d[v]的值
and we replaced it with some other d of u
然后我们用别的值d[u]
plus the weight of the edge from u to v.
加上(u,v)来代替它
And somehow, this made it invalid.
然后这时 这个不成立了
So, d of v is somehow less than this.
d[v]不知为何 比它要小
We just set d of v to this.
我们设d[v]等于这个
So, this must be less than delta of s, v.
那么这个肯定小于δ(s,v)
The claim is that that's not possible because,
但这个命题不可能成立
let me rewrite a little bit.
让我来把它改写一下
We have d of u plus w of (u,v).
我们有d[u]加上w(u,v)
And, we have our induction hypothesis,
我们有归纳假设
which holds on u, u of some other vertex.
在u上是成立的 u和别的一些顶点
We know that d of u is at least delta of s, u.
我们知道d[u]最小等于δ(s,u)
So, this has to be at least delta of s, u plus w of u, v.
所以 这个不小于δ(s,u)加上w(u,v)
Now, what about this w of u, v?
w(u,v)是多少？
Well, that's some path from u to v.
从u到v有一些路径
So, it's got to be bigger than the shortest path or equal.
它大于或等于最短路径的
So certainly, this is greater than or equal to delta of u, v.
所以当然它大于等于δ(u,v)
OK, it could be larger if there's some multi-edged path
好的 如果这有较小权值的多边路径的话
that has a smaller total weight,
它还能更大
but it's certainly no smaller than delta of u, v.
但是它当然是不会小于δ(u,v)
And, this looks like a good summation,
这个和看起来正合我意
delta of S to u, and u to v is a triangle inequality, yeah.
δ(s,u)加上δ(u,v)就是三角形不等式 耶
So, that is, it's upside down here.
就是说 它反过来了
But, the triangle s, u, u to v,
三角形不等式 δ(s,u) δ(u,v)
so this is only longer than S to v.
所以这个只能大于δ(s,v)
OK, so we have this thing,
好的 我们有了这个式子
which is simultaneously greater than or equal to
同一时间 它大于等于
the shortest path weight from s to v,
s到v的最短路径的权值
and also strictly less than the shortest path weight from S to v.
又严格小于s到v的最短路径的权值
So, that's a contradiction.
那么 这里出现了矛盾
Maybe contradiction isn't the most intuitive way to proceed.
也许反证法不是最直观的方法
The intuition, here, is whenever you assign d of v,
这里的直观推断是 当你给出d[v]
you have a path in mind.
你脑海里就有了一条路径
You inductively had a path from s to u.
你用归纳方法想 s和u之间有一条路径
Then you added this edge.
然后你加上这条边
So, that was a real path.
而这条路径真实存在
We always know that every path has weight
我们知道每条路径的权值
greater than or equal to the shortest path.
总是大于或等于最短路径
So, it should be true, and here's the inductive proof.
而它应该为真 这就是归纳法的证明
All right, moving right along,
好的 我们继续
so this was an easy warm-up.
这只是简单的热身运动
We have greater than or equal to.
我们有大于等于
Now we have to prove less than or equal to
现在我们要证明在算法最后
at the end of the algorithm.
它是小于等于的
This is true all the time;
这个总是成立的
less than or equal to will only be true at the end.
小于等于只会在最后才会成立
So, we are not going to prove less than or equal to quite yet.
那么 我们现在不准备证明小于等于是对的
We're going to prove another lemma, which again,
我们接下来证明另一个引理 再有
so both of these lemmas are useful for other algorithms, too.
这些引理对其它的算法也是有用的
So, we're sort of building some shortest path theory
那么 我们建立起最短路径的理论
that we can apply later.
我们以后会用到的
This one will give you some intuition about why relaxation,
而这个则会让你直观地理解为什么要松弛
not only is it not bad, it's actually good.
不仅是它并不水 而是相当虎
Not only does it not screw up anything,
它不仅没有拖后腿
but it also makes progress in the following sense.
而且还能造福社会
So, suppose you knew the shortest path from s to some vertex.
所以 假设你知道s到某个顶点的最短路径
OK, so you go from s to some other vertices.
那好 那你从s到其它某个顶点
Then you go to u. Then you go to v.
然后你走到u 走到v
Suppose that is a shortest path from s to v.
假设s到v有一条最短路径
OK, and also suppose that we already know
好的 再假设我们已知
in d of u the shortest path weight from s to u.
d[u]是从s到u最短路径的权值
So, suppose we have this equality.
那么 假设我们有这么一个等式
We now know that we always have a greater than or equal to.
虽然它应该总是大于等于的
Suppose they are equal for u, OK,
但假设对u是相等的 好吧
the vertex just before v in the shortest path.
在v的前一个点时 它是最短路径
OK, and suppose we relax that edge, (u,v),
好的 假设我们松弛了这条边(u,v)
OK, which is exactly this step.
好的 刚好是这一步
This is relaxing the edge, (u,v).
松弛了这条边(u,v)
But we'll just call it relaxation here.
但我们叫它为松了个弛
After that relaxation, d of v equals delta of (s,v).
在松了个弛后 d[v]等于δ(s,v)
So, if we had the correct answer for u, and we relax (u,v),
那么 如果我们u是正确答案 我们松弛(u,v)
then we get the correct answer for v.
那么我们也会得到v的正确答案
OK, this is good news.
好的 这是个好消息
It means, if inductively we can somehow get the right answer for u,
这说明 归纳地看 如果能给u找到正确答案
now we know how to get the right answer for v.
那么 我们就知道怎么得到v的正确答案
In the algorithm, we don't actually know
在这个算法里 我们实际上不知道
what the vertex just before v in the shortest path is,
v在最短路径上的前一个点是什么
but in the analysis we can pretty much know that.
但是在分析过程中我们很清楚
So, we have to prove this lemma.
所以 我们需要证明这个引理
This is actually even easier than the previous one:
这个实际上比上一个证明要简单
don't even need induction
甚至还用不着数学归纳法
because you just work through what's going on in relaxation,
因为你只是研究松弛的过程
and it's true.
而且它是成立的
So, here we go.
那么 我们继续
So, we're interested in this value, delta of s v.
我们注意这个数 δ(s,v)
And we know what the shortest path is.
我们知道最短路径是什么
So, the shortest path weight is the weight of this path.
那么最短路径的权值 就是这条路径的权值
OK, so we can write down some equality here.
好的 我们这里可以写下这个等式
Well, I'm going to split out the first part of the path
我打算把这条路径的第一部分截出来
and the last part of the path.
还有路径的最后一部分
So, we have, I'll say, the weight from s,
那么 我们有 权值从s到...
so, this part of the path from s to u,
这部分就等于s到u的值
plus the weight of this edge, u, v.
加上w(u,v)
Remember, we could write w of a path,
记住 我们记路径的w
and that was the total weight of all those edges.
它等于所有这些边的权值的总和
So, what is this, the weight of this path from S to u?
所以 这个是多少 从s到u的权值？
Or, what property should I use to figure out what that value is?
或者说 这个值能用什么性质算出来？
Yeah?
什么？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:...
[Prof]:s to v is the shortest path, right?
[教授]:s到v是最短路径吧？
So, by optimal substructure,
根据最优子结构
from s to u is also a shortest path.
s到u也是一个最短路径
So, this is delta of s, u.
所以 这个是δ(s,v)
Cool.
漂亮！
We'll hold on for now. That's all we're going to say.
我们先这么认为 这就是我们要说的
On the other hand, we know
另一方面 我们知道
from this lemma that no matter what we do,
由引理可知无论我们在做什么
d of v is greater than or equal to delta of s, v.
d[v]总是大于等于δ(s,v)
So, let's write that down.
那么 我们记下这点
So, there's a few cases,
这里有几种情况
and this will eliminate some of the cases.
而且其中一些情况要除去
By that lemma correctness one,
根据那个证明了的引理
we know that d of v is greater than or equal to delta of s, v.
我们知道d[v]大于等于δ(s,v)
So, it's either equal or greater than at all times.
所以 它总是大于等于的
So, I'm thinking about the time before we do the relaxation,
我想到在我们做松弛之前的那一次
this (u,v).
这个(u,v)
So, at that point, this is certainly true.
在这个点上 这个肯定是对的
So, either they're equal before relaxation or it's greater.
不管它在松弛之前是大于还是等于
OK, if they are equal before relaxation, we're happy
好的 如果它们是等于的话 我们就爽了
because relaxation only decreases values by correctness one.
因为松弛每次都只会减少之前确定的值
It can't get any smaller than this,
它没法比它还小
so after relaxation it will also be equal.
所以松弛之后它会是相等的
OK, so in this case we're done.
好的 我们证明完这种情况
So, that's a trivial case.
这种情况意义不大
So let's now suppose that
现在我们假设
d of v is greater than delta of s, v before relaxation.
d[v]在松弛前是大于δ(s,v)
That's perfectly valid.
这个肯定可以有
Hopefully now we fix it.
我们现在想要证明它
OK, well the point is, we know this delta s, v.
好的 有一点就是 我们知道δ(s,v)
It is this sum. OK, we also know this.
它就是这个和 好的 我们知道这点
So, we plug this, delta of s, u we know is d of u.
那么 我们把它代入 我们知道δ(s,u)就等于d[u]
And, we have this w(u,v).
然后 我们有这个w(u,v)
So, delta of s, v is d of u plus w of (u,v)
所以 δ(s,v)等于d[u]加上w(u,v)
because we are assuming we have this shortest path structure
因为我们假设我们有这个最短路径结构
where you go from s to u,
就是你先从s走到u
and then you follow the edge, (u,v).
然后再走(u,v)这条边
So, we know this.
我们知道这个
So, we know d of v is greater than d of u plus w of (u,v).
我们知道d[v]大于d[u]加上w(u,v)的和
By golly, that's this condition in relaxation.
哎哟喂 这就是松弛的条件来的
So, we're just checking, relaxation actually does something here.
好好回想下吧 松弛在这儿做了些什么
OK, if you had the wrong distance estimate,
好的 如果你估算了一个错误距离
this if condition is satisfied.
如果满足了这个条件
Therefore, we do this.
那么 我们会这么做
So, in this case, we relax.
在这种情况下 我们使用松弛
So, I'm just relaxing.
我只要松弛一下
Then, we set d of v to d of u plus w(u,v),
那么 我们就令d[v]等于d[u]加上w(u,v)
which is what we want.
也就是我们想要的
OK, so we set d of v to d of u plus w of (u,v).
好的 我们令d[v]等于d[u]加上w(u,v)
And, this equals, as we said here, delta of S, v,
而它就等于 我们这里说的δ(s,v)
which is what we wanted to prove.
这正是我们想证明的
Done.
搞定
OK, I'm getting more and more excited
好的 我现在越来越兴奋了
as we get into the meat of this proof.
因为我们已经看到证明的主线了
Any questions so far?
有什么问题吗？
Good. Now comes the hard part.
好 接下来讲最难的那部分
These are both very easy lemmas, right?
这两个都是非常简单的引理 对吧？
I'll use these two boards.
我待会儿要用到这两面黑板
We don't need these proofs anymore.
我们现在不需要这些证明了
We just need these statements:
我们只留下这些命题
correctness one, correctness lemma;
第一个正确性和正确性引理
great names.
好名字
So, now finally we get to correctness two.
现在 终于轮到第二个正确性
So, we had one and one and a half.
我们这儿有一个和一个半
So, I guess correctness is, itself,
我觉得正确性 它本身
a mini-trilogy, the mini-series.
就是个迷你三部曲 是一个迷你系列
So correctness two says when the algorithm is done,
第二个正确性讲的就是 当这个算法结束时
we have the right answer.
我们就得出正确答案
This is really correctness.
这就是真正的正确性
But, it's going to build on correctness one and correctness lemma.
但是 它还要基于第一个正确性和正确性引理
So, we want d of v to equal delta of s, v for all vertices, v
在算法结束时 我们要有对于所有v
at the end of the algorithm.
d[v]等于δ(s,v)
That is clearly our goal.
很明显 这就是我们的目标
Now, this theorem is assuming that
这个定理先假设了...
all of the weights are nonnegative, just to repeat.
所有的边的权值都是非负的
It doesn't assume anything else.
除此之外没有别的条件
So, it's going to get the infinities right.
所以 出现正无穷是合理的
But, if there are minus infinities, all bets are off.
但是如果出现负无穷 那一切都是无用功了
OK, even if there's any negative weight edge anywhere,
如果有负权值 即便是哪里都好
it's not going to do the right thing necessarily.
它都一定不会有好事
But, assuming all the weights are nonnegative,
但是 假设所有的边都是非负的
which is reasonable if they're measuring time.
用它们来表示时间代价就很合理了
Usually it costs money to travel along edges.
通常要这些边走是要花费金钱的
They don't pay you to do it. But who knows?
没人会给你过路费 但还说不定
So, I need just to say a few things.
我现在需要讲一点东西
One of the things we've mentioned somewhere along the way is
其中一个 我们一路过来都有提及的
when you add a vertex to S, you never change its weight.
当你把一个顶点加到S中时 你不用改变它的权值
OK, that actually requires proof.
好的 这其实是要证明的
I'm just going to state it here.
我只是想在这里说明一下
It's not hard to see. d of v doesn't change.
其实不难发现 d[v]不会改变
OK, this is essentially an induction once v is added to S.
当v被加进S里时 这其实也是归纳结果
OK, this will actually followed by something we'll say in a moment.
好的 这个跟待会儿要讲的东西有关
OK, so all I really care about is when a vertex is added to S,
我所关心的是 当一个点被加入到S中时
we better have the right estimate because after that,
我们最好有一个正确的估算 因为之后
we're not going to change it, let's say.
我们不会改变它了
OK, we could define the algorithm that way.
好的 我们可以这样了定义算法
We are not, but we could.
虽然可以 但我们不这么做
I'll say more about this in a second.
这个等下会再详细讲
So, all we care about is whether d of v equals delta of s, v.
所以 我们所关心的是d[v]等于δ(s,v)
That's what we want to prove.
这就是我们想证明的
So, it's clearly that. It should be true at the end.
很明显 它在最后应该是真的
But, it suffices to prove that
但是 我们足以证明
it holds when v is added to S, to capital S.
当v被加入大写S里的时候它是成立的
OK, this actually implies the first statement.
好的 这暗示了第一个命题
It has sort of a funny implication.
它其实暗示了一些东西
But, if we can prove this, that d of v equals delta of s, v,
但是 如果我们能证明d[v]等于δ(s,v)
when you add to S, we know relaxation only decreases value.
当你(把v)加到S时 我们知道松弛只会把权值降低
So, it can't get any smaller.
那么它没法变得更小
It would be from correctness one.
这点从第一个正确性得出的
Correctness one says we can't get any smaller than delta.
第一个正确性表明 我们没有比δ(s,v)更小的了
So, if we get a equality at that point,
所以 如果我们在那个点上得出了等式
we'll have a equality from then on.
那之后 我们还是有这个等式的
So, that actually implies d of v never changes after that point.
所以 这说明那点松弛过后 d[v]不会再改变了
OK, so we're going to prove this.
好的 我们准备证明这个
Good. Well, suppose it isn't true.
好的 假设它不成立
So this would be a proof by a contradiction.
这又是一个反证法
Suppose for contradiction that this fails to hold.
假设出现了矛盾 使命题不成立
And, let's look at the first failure.
然后 我们看到第一个出错点
Suppose u is the first vertex——
假设u是第一个点
——that's about to be added to S.
正准备要加到S里去的
I want to consider the time right before it's added to S,
我想研究 它还没被加入到S前的那一刻
for which we don't have what we want.
那时 我们没有想要的结果
These are not equal.
这些是不相等的
d of u does not equal delta of s, u.
d[u]不等于δ(s,u)
Well, if they're not equal,
好的 如果它们不相等
we know from correctness one that
我们从第一个正确性得知
d of v is strictly greater than delta of s, u,
d[v]是严格大于δ(s,u)
so, d of u.
说错了 是d[u]
So, we have d of u is strictly greater than delta of s, u.
我们有d[u]是严格大于δ(s,u)
OK, that's the beginning of the proof,
这就是证明的开始部分
nothing too exciting yet, just some warm-up.
没有什么特别 只算是准备工夫
OK, but this, used already correctness one.
好的 这已经用到了第一个正确性
I think that's the only time that we use it in this proof.
我想在这个证明中 只会用到它一次
So I sort of just want to draw picture of what's going on.
我想用画图来解释这个过程
But I need a little bit of description.
但我还得加上一点描述
So, let's look at the shortest path.
我们看到这条最短路径
Somehow, d of u is greater than the shortest path.
因为某种原因 d[u]大于最短路径
So, consider the shortest path or a shortest path.
所以 考虑到某条 或某一条最短路径
Let p be a shortest path, not just any shortest path,
设p为其中一条最短路径 而不是任意一条
but the shortest path from s to u.
它是从s到u的最短路径
OK, so that means that
好的 这说明
the weight of this path is the shortest path weight.
这条路径的权值等于最短路径的权值
So, we have some equations for what's going on here.
所以 我们可以写下一些方程
So, we care about delta of s, u.
那么 我们关心的是δ(s,u)
Here's a path with that weight.
这条路径的权值是这个数
It's got to be one because shortest paths exist here;
它肯定会有 因为最短路径存在
slight exceptional cases if it's a plus infinity,
有个例外就是当它为正无穷时
but I'm not going to worry about that.
但是我们不用担心这个
So, let me draw a picture somewhere.
所以 让我们把图画出来
So, we have s. We have u.
我们有s跟u
Here is the shortest path from s to u. That's p.
这是从s到u的的最短路径 这就是p
No idea what it looks like so far.
现在 还不知道它长什么样的
Now, what we also have is the notion of capital S.
好的 我们还有一个大写S符号
So, I'm going to draw capital S.
我把大写S画出来
So, this is big S.
那么 这个是大写S
We know that little s is in big S.
我们知道小写s是在大写S集合里的
We know that u is not yet in big S.
u暂时还不在大写S里
So, I haven't screwed up anything yet, right?
目前 我还没做错事吧？
This path starts in S and leaves it at some point
这条路径从S里面开始 到某个点时会离开S
because until we are about to add u to S,
因为最后 我们要将u加入S中之前
so it hasn't happened yet, so u is not in S.
但现在还没 暂时u还没在S中
Fine. What I want to do is look at the first place here
好的 我想观察的第一个地方是这里
where the path, p, exits S.
路径p离开S的地方
So, there is some vertex here. Let's call it x.
那么 这里有一个顶点 我设它为x
There's some vertex here. We'll call it y.
这里又有一个点 我设它为y
OK, possibly x equals S.
好的 x可能等于s
Possibly y equals u.
y可能等于u
But it's got to exit somewhere,
但可以肯定 路径p是在某处离开S的
because it starts inside and ends up outside.
因为它是从里面开始 在外面结束的
And it's a finite path.
而且这是一个有限的图
OK, so consider the first time it happens;
那考虑第一次离开的时候
not the second time, the first.
而不是第二次 是第一次
OK, so consider the first edge, (x,y), where p exits capital S.
好的 考虑p第一次离开S时 是通过边(x,y)
The shortest path from s to u exits capital S.
这是从s到u的最短路径 它离开了大写S
It's got to happen somewhere.
它肯定会离开的
Cool, now, what do we know? Little x is in S.
好的 现在我们知道什么？x是在S里面
So, it has the right answer because u,
所以它是正确的  因为u...
we were about to add u to S,
我们准备将u加到S中
and that was the first violation of something in S
而那是第一个出错的地方
that has the wrong d of x estimate.
它的估算距离是错误的
So, d of x equals delta of s, x.
所以d[x]等于δ(s,x)
Because we are looking at the first violation,
因为我们考虑的是第一个出错的地方
x is something that got added before.
x是之前就加进S里的
So, by induction on time,
所以 根据归纳法上的时间
or because we had the first violation,
或者说 因为这是第一个出错点
d of x equals the shortest path weight from S to x.
d[x]依然是s到x的最短路径的权值
So, that's good news.
这是个好消息
Now we are trying to apply this lemma.
现在我们想要运用这个引理
It's the only thing left to do.
这个是剩下唯一要做的事情
We haven't used this lemma for anything.
我们到目前还没用过这个引理
So, we have the setup.
我们有了这个引理
If we already know that one of the d values is the right answer,
如果已经知道某个d值是正确的
and we relaxed the edge that goes out from it,
我们松弛那条边 然后往下走
then we get another right answer.
就会得到另外一个正确答案
So that's what I want to argue over here.
这里是我想讨论的地方
We know that the d of x equals this weight because,
我们知道d[x]等于这个权值因为
again, subpaths of shortest paths are shortest paths.
再一次 最短路径的子路径也是最短路径
We have optimal substructure,
我们有最优子结构
so this is a shortest path, from S to x.
所以这个是从s到x的最短路径
It might not be the only one, but it is one.
它可能不止一个 但它是其中一个
So we know that matches.
那么 我们知道它没错了
Now, I want to think about relaxing this edge, (x,y).
现在我想松弛这条边(x,y)
Well, x is in capital S.
呃 x在大写S里
And, the algorithm says,
然后 这个算法说
whenever you add a vertex, u, to the big set, S,
当你把顶点u加入到集合S中时
you relax all the edges that go out from there.
你都要把它所有外连的边松弛一遍
OK, so when we added x to S,
好的 但我们把x加入S中时
and we now look far in the future,
我们看看之后会如何
we're about to add some other vertex.
我们准备加入别的一些的顶点
Right after we added x to S, we relax this edge, (x,y),
就在我们把x加入S以后 我们松弛这条边(x,y)
because we relaxed every edge that goes out from x,
因为我们要松弛每一条从x出来的边
OK, whatever they were. Some of them went into S.
无论是哪一条 它们有一些是在S里面的
Some of them went out. Here's one of them.
有一些跑到外面去 这就是其中一条
So, when we added x to S, we got x in S.
但我们往S里加入x时 我们有x在S里
When we added x to S, we relaxed the edge, (x,y).
当我们往S里加入x后 我们松弛这条边(x,y)
OK, so now we're going to use the lemma.
好的 现在我们要用到这个引理
So, by the correctness lemma
于是 根据正确性引理
——What do you get?
可以得出什么？
Well, we add this correct shortest path weight to x now.
我们将这个正确的最短路径的权值 赋给x
We relax the edge, (x,y).
然后 将(x,y)松弛
So, now we should have the correct shortest path weight for y.
现在我们应该得到了 y的正确的最短路径权值
d of y equals delta of s, y.
d[y]等于δ(s,y)
OK, this is sometime in the past.
好的 它在某个时候点是成立的
In particular, now, it should still be true
而现在它仍为真
because once you get down to the right answer you never change it.
因为一旦你得到了正确答案 你就不能改变它了
OK, we should be done. OK, why are we done?
好的 我们已经证明完了 为什么就完了？
Well, what else do we know here?
我们还知道什么东西？
We assumed something for contradiction,
我们假设某些东西要矛盾
so we better contradict that.
所以 我们要反驳这点
We assume somehow, d of u is strictly greater than delta of s, u.
我们假设因为某种原因 d[u]严格大于δ(s,u)
So, d of u here
所以这里的d[u]
is strictly greater than the length of this whole path.
是严格大于这条（最短）路径的权值的
Well, we don't really know whether u equals y.
我们实际上不知道u是否就是y
It could, could not.
可能是 可能不是
And, but what do we know about this shortest path from S to y?
但是我们关心的是S到y的最短路径是什么？
Well, it could only be shorter than from S to u
它只可能比S到u要短
because it's a subpath.
因为它是一条子路径
And it's the shortest path
而且它是一条最短路径
because it's the subpath of the shortest path.
因为它就是最短路径的子路径
The shortest path from S to y
从S到y的最短路径
has to be less than or equal to the shortest path from S to u.
必须小于或等于S到u的最短路径
OK, S to y: less than or equal to s, u,
好的 S到y 小于或者等于s到u
OK, just because the subpath.
好的 因为它是子路径
I'm closer. I've got delta of s, u now.
越来越接近了 我有一个δ(s,u)
Somehow, I want to involve d of u.
但我想跟d[u]扯上关系
So, I want to relate d of y to d of u.
而我想将d[y]和d[u]联系起来
What do I know about d of u?
关于d[u]我知道什么？
Yeah?
什么？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:...
d of u is smaller because we have a Min heap, yeah.
d[u]会更小 因为我们用的是最小堆
We always chose u, it is erased, it's way down here.
我们选择的是u 好像擦掉了 噢 它在这儿
We chose u. This is the middle of the algorithm.
我们选择的是u 这是算法的中间部分
It's the reason I kept this to be the minimum key.
这就是为什么我保留的是最小的键值
This is keyed on d. So, we know that at this moment,
键值对应的是d值 在这个时候
when we're trying to add u to S, right,
当我们是要将u加到S 好的
y is not in S, and u is not in S.
y不再S里 u也不在S里
They might actually be the same vertex.
实际上 它们可能是同一个顶点
But both of these vertices, same or not, are outside S.
但这俩点 相同或不相同 都在S外面
We chose u because d of u has the smallest d estimate.
我们选择u因为d[u]的估算值最小
So, d of y has to be greater than or equal to d of u.
所以d[y]必须大于等于d[u]
It might be equal if they're the same vertex,
如果它们是同一点的话它们相等
but it's got to be greater than or equal to.
但是它是大于或等于
So, d of y here is greater than or equal to d of u.
所以 d[y]是大于或等于d[u]
So, here we're using the fact that we actually made a greedy choice.
事实上 我们这里采取了贪心策略
It's the one place we're using the greedy choice.
它是我们使用贪心策略的地方
Better use it somewhere because
这么用的好处是
you can't just take an arbitrary vertex and declare it to be done.
你不能随便选一个点 然后说这个点已经搞定了
You've got to take the greedy one.
你必须要贪心地选择最好的
OK, now we have d of u is less than or equal to delta of s, u,
因为我们已经有d[u]小于等于δ(s,u)了
which contradicts this.
所以跟它矛盾了
OK, sort of magical that that all just worked out.
好的 这样就全部完成了 果然有点科幻
But sort of like the previous proofs,
但就像前面的证明
you just see what happens and it works.
你只需看它到底发生了什么
OK, that's the approximation.
好的 这就是估算过程
The only real idea here is to look at this edge.
重要的思想是观察这条边
In fact, you could look at this edge too.
实际上 你也可以观察这条边
But let's look at some edge that comes from S and goes out of S,
但是我们观察的是从S里出来又走出S的边
and argue that while x has to be correct,
并讨论 当x是正确时
and what we made x correct, y had to be correct,
我们令x正确的话 y也是正确的
and now, why the hell are we looking at u?
那我们还追着u不放干什么？
y is the thing you should have looked at.
y才是你们需要注意的地方
And, there you get a contradiction
这样 你就发现了矛盾
because y had the right answer.
因为y有了正确答案
If u equals y, that's fine,
如果u等于y 那很好
or if u and y were sort of equally good,
或如果u和y都差不多好
that's also fine if all these weights were zero.
这样也不错 如果权值都为0的话
So, the picture might actually look like this.
那么 这幅图可能真的会是这样子
But, in that case, d of u is the correct answer.
但是 这种情况下 d[u]就是正确答案
It was delta SU. We assumed that it wasn't.
它等于δ(s,u) 而我们假设它不是
That's where we're getting a contradiction.
这就是我们找到的矛盾的地方
Pretty clear? Go over this proof.
清楚了没？重温一下这个证明
It's a bit complicated, naturally.
有点复杂也理所当然
OK, we have a little bit more to cover, some easier stuff.
好的 我们还要讲一点简单的东西
OK, the first thing is what's the running time of this algorithm?
第一个是 这个算法的运行时间是多少？
I'll do this very quick
我要快速解决
because we're actually seen this many times before last class.
因为实际上 我们已经在上次课之前见过很多遍了
There was some initialization.
它有个初始化
The initialization, which is no longer here, is linear time.
初始化 但现在擦掉了 它是线性时间的
No big deal.
不是大问题
OK, extract Min.
好的 选取最小值
Well, that's some data structure.
好 这里有个数据结构
So, we have something like size of V.
我们有个大小为V的东西
Every vertex we extract the Min once, and that's it.
对每个顶点我们取出最小值 这里就是
So, size of V, extract mins.
V大小的东西 选最小值
OK, so that's pretty simple.
好的 这个相当简单
OK, then we had this main loop.
好的 这个是主循环
This is a completely conceptual operation.
这完全是概念上的操作
S is not actually used in the algorithm.
这个算法实际上没用到S
It's just for thinking.
只是作为一个思路
OK, so this takes zero time.
好的 那么这里耗时为0
Got to love it.
免费什么的最喜欢了
OK, and now the heart is here.
好的 核心部分是这里
So, how many times does this loop iterate?
这个循环需要迭代多少次？
That's the degree of u.
它等于u的度数
So, what is the total number of times
所以 我们花在松弛操作上的
that we execute a relaxation step?
总时间是多少？
It doesn't necessarily mean we do this,
它并不是代表我们真的做了这一步
but we at least execute this body.
但我们至少执行了这部分
Over the whole algorithm, how many times do we do this?
整个算法里 我们一共做了这步多少次？
Every vertex, we look at all the outgoing edges from there.
对每个顶点 我们都观察它连出来的边
So, the total would be?
那么总数会是多少？
Number of edges, yeah.
等于边的数目 好
So, this number of edges iterations.
总共有边数次的迭代
OK, this is essentially the handshaking lemma we saw last time,
好的 这实际上是我们上次学到的握手引理
but for directed graphs.
但这是在有向图上
And we are only looking at the outgoing edges.
而且我们只是观察外连的边
So, it's not a factor of two here
所以它这里不是系数2
because you're only outgoing from one side.
因为你只从一个方向出来
So, we have number of reiterations.
我们有这么多次的迭代
In the worst case, we do a decreased key for everyone.
在最坏情况下 我们要减小每一个键值
So, at most: E decreased keys.
所以最多会有E次减小键值的操作
OK, so the time is, well, we have v extract Mins,
好的 所以运行时间是 我们还有v次取最小值
so the time to do an extract Min, whatever that is.
取出最小值耗费的时间 不管多少
And we have E decreased keys, whatever that is,
减小键值耗费的时间 也不管多少
and this is exactly the running time we had
这个就刚好是我们上次
for Prim's algorithm for a minimum spanning tree last time.
讲的Prim最小生成树算法的运行时间
And, it depends what data structure you use,
然后 根据你用的数据结构
what running time you get.
运行时间也有所变化
So, I'm going to skip the whole table here.
那么 我准备要跳过这整个表
But, if you use an array, the final running time will be V^2
但是 如果你用一个数组 最后的运行时间等于V^2
because you have order of v extract Min,
因为有v阶的取最小数的操作
and you have constant time decreased key.
然后你们要用常数时间来降低的键值
If you use a binary heap, which we know and love,
如果你用的是二叉堆 也就是我们的最爱
then we have order log v for each operation.
每次操作就便成了log v了
And so, this is V plus E log V.
然后 这个是V+E的和乘以log v
And, so that's what we know how to do.
然后 这就是我们所知道要做的
And, if you use this fancy data structure called a Fibonacci heap,
如果你用的是一个叫做斐波那契堆 这种高档货的话
you get constant time decreased key amortized.
降低键值操作可以平摊为常数级
And, you get an E plus v log v
你得到E＋vlog v
worst case bound on the running time.
作为最坏情况的运行时间
So, this is the best we know how to solve
那么 这就是我所知道的最好方法
shortest paths without any extra assumptions,
来解决无条件的最短路径算法
single source shortest paths with non-negative edge weights
也就是单源无负边的情况
in general.
一般来说
OK, this is almost as good and this is sometimes better than that.
好的 这个基本上算好的 这个有时候比那个要好
But these are essentially irrelevant
但这些实际上是无关的
except that you know how to do these.
除非你知道怎么做这些了
You don't know how to do a Fibonacci heap
你不知道怎么去建立一个斐波那契堆
unless you read that in the chapter of the book.
除非你读过书上面的那一章
That's why we mention the top two running times.
这就是为什么我要说上面两个的运行时间
OK, I want to talk briefly about a simpler case,
好的 我想谈谈一个简单的情况
which you may have seen before.
你们之前可能已经见过
And so it's sort of fun to connect this up
有件很有趣的事情是 将这个算法
to breadth first search in a graph.
跟广度优先搜索关联起来
So, I mean that ends Dijkstra, so to speak.
我的意思是Dijkstra结束时 就是说
But now I want to think about a special case
假设有一个特殊情况
where the graph is unweighted,
图上的边都是没有权值的
meaning w of (u,v) equals one for all vertices, u and v.
意味着w(u,v)都等于1
OK, suppose we had that property.
好的 假设有这样的条件
Can we do any better than Dijkstra?
我们怎么做得比Dijkstra要好？
Can we do better than this running time?
我们还能比这个时间更快吗？
Well, we probably have to look at all the edges and all the vertices.
好的 我们可能要看看所有的边和所有的点
So, the only thing I'm questioning is this log v.
那么 唯一一个疑问就是log v
Can I avoid that?
我怎么避免这个？
I gave away the answer a little bit.
我剧透了一点答案了
The answer is called breadth first search, or BFS,
这个答案就是用广度优先搜索 即BFS
which you have probably seen before, next to depth first search,
你们可能之前就见过了 跟在深度搜索后面
it's one of the standard ways to look at the graph.
它是遍历图的标准方法之一
But we can say a little bit more than you may have seen before.
但我们会说得比之前多一点
Breadth for search is actually Dijkstra's algorithm:
广度优先搜索实际上就是Dijkstra算法
kind of nifty. There are two changes.
有点俏皮 它有两个改动
The first change is that
第一个改动是
breadth for search does not use a priority queue.
广度优先搜索不使用优先队列
I'll just tell you what it uses instead.
我来告诉你 它用的是什么
You can use a queue
你可以用一个队列
first in first out honest-to-goodness queue
先进先出的队列
instead of a priority queue.
来代替优先队列
OK, it turns out that works.
好的 它实测可行
Instead of doing extract Min,
每次取队列的第一个值
you just take the first thing off the queue.
来代替取最小值
Instead of doing decreased key,
它不需要减小键值
OK, here's a subtlety.
好的 这地方有些微妙
But, this if statement changes a little bit.
但是命题要改变的就是这一点
So, here is the relaxation step.
那么 这是松弛操作
So, in order to relax, you say this much simpler thing.
这样松弛就变得更简单了
If we haven't visited v yet,
如果说我们还没遇到过v
then we declare it to have the shortest path weight,
那一旦接触到它时 它就是最短路径的权值了
say, d of v is d of u plus one,
也就是说 d[v]=d[u]+1
which is the weight of the edge, (u,v).
也就是这条边的权值(u,v)
And we add v to the end of the queue.
然后我们把v加到队列的末尾
So, now, we start with the queue empty.
现在 我们从空队列开始
Actually, it will just contain the vertex, S,
实际上 它包含了起点s
because that's the only thing we know the shortest path for.
因为这是唯一已知的最短路径
So, the queue is just for,
那么 这个队列是用来
I know the shortest path of this thing.
当我知道这样一个最短路径时
Just deal with it when you can
那就对它下手
look at all the outgoing edges when you can.
观察它连到外面的边
So, initially that's just s.
所以一开始这里只有s
You say, well, for all the outgoing edges, s has zero.
对于所有向外连的边 s为0
All the outgoing edges from there have weight one.
所有连到外面的边的权值为1
The shortest path weight from the source is one.
所以从源点到这里的最短路径的权值为1
You certainly can't do any better than that if all the weights are one
你肯定没法找到比1更好的了
OK, so we add all those vertices to the end of the queue.
好的 那么我们把这些顶点都加到队列的尾部
Then, we process things in order,
然后 我们按顺序来处理
and we just keep incrementing, if their value is d of u,
然后不断加1 如果它等于d[u]
add one to it. That's d of v.
给它加上一 那就是d[v]
And then we are going to add v to S in the next
然后我们接下来把v加到S里
when we get to it in the queue.
每当我们在队列里读到它的时候
OK, that is breadth for search, very simple.
好的 广度优先搜索 非常简单
And, you can look at the text for the algorithm
然后 你可以看看算法的下一步
and for an example because I don't have time to cover that.
我直接举例子了 因为没时间讲它了
But the key thing is that the time is faster.
但是关键是运行时间更小了
The time is order V plus E because
时间等于O(V+E)因为
as before, we only look at each edge once
跟以前一样 每条边我们都只看到过一次
we look at all the outgoing edges from all the vertices.
我们观察所有从顶点出来的边
As soon as we set d of v to something, it will remain that.
一旦设d[v]为某个值 它就不会改变
We never touch it. We are going to add it to S.
我再也不会改动它 我们直接它加入到S中
That only happens once.
而这也只发生一次
So, this if statement, and so on,
所以这个if语句 还有其他的
in the in-queuing, is done order E times,
队列插入操作 一共做了E阶次
or actually E times, exactly.
或者是刚好是E次
An in-queuing to a queue, and de-queuing from a queue,
队列的插入 以及队列的出列操作
that's what we use instead of extract Min, take constant time,
这代替了取最小值的操作 花费常数时间
so the total running time,
所以总的时间是
number of vertices plus the number of edges.
顶点的数目加上边的数目
OK, not so obvious that this works,
好像不是显然有效
but you can prove that it works using the Dijkstra analysis.
但你可以用Dijkstra的分析来证明它有效
All you have to do is prove that the FIFO queue
你要证明的就是FIFO队列做的事情
does exactly the same thing as the priority queue.
跟优先队列做的事情是一样的
Once you know that, by the correctness of Dijkstra
一旦证明了它 根据Dijkstra的正确性
you get the correctness of breadth first search.
你也可以得到广度搜索的正确性
So, not only is breadth first search finding all the vertices,
所以 广度搜索不仅能找到所有的点
which is maybe what you normally use it for,
这是你通常用到的功能
but it finds the shortest path weights
它还能找到最短路径
from S to every other vertex when the weights are all one.
起点为S到其他所有的点 如果边长都为1的话
So, there we go: introduction to shortest paths.
所以 这就是最短路径序章
Next time we'll deal with negative weights.
下一次课我们会处理负环的问题